one way of framing it is that we are
smack dab in the middle of a global
scale civilization level collapse now if
we do our job right it will be a
transition to something else but right
now we're you know collapse is a good
way of thinking about what's happening
and what I mean by global scale is that
for the very first time in human history
starting somewhere or maybe in the 80s
all human beings were roughly and
trained in a single civilization
framework that's never happened before
so so to begin what I would like to do
is I would like to express my personal
thanks to president Donald James Trump
no I'm I'm serious because the 2016
election did more to shake good people
from the dogmatic slumbers than any
event that I am aware yeah
it's a it's actually been a very big
deal I've felt a significant increase in
energy it significant increase in a
willingness to accept the fact that the
best way to describe our current
circumstances is that is up
it's actually a deep insight because it
recognizes simultaneously that things
aren't working and we haven't got a good
way of describing exactly what is going
wrong and that's like the first step to
real wisdom so it's a good thing that
that's happening we're gonna spend a
little bit of time trying to talk about
what we've been doing and trying to put
some frameworks around what is
up might mean and how we might go
about visioning what a good positive
direction might look like and I'm gonna
start I think with just a short piece
and then Daniel will go into some depth
on the nature of the problem and then
Forest will actually introduce us to an
example of what a piece of the solution
likely looks like and something that he
calls transcendental design so one way
of framing it is that we are smack dab
in the middle of a global scale
civilization level collapse now if we do
our job right it will be a transition to
something else but right now we're you
know collapse is a good way of thinking
about what's happening and what I mean
by global scale is that for the very
first time in human history starting
somewhere or maybe in the 80s all human
beings were roughly and trained in a
single civilization framework that's
never happened before
and then now that civilization framework
is reaching its end of life and what I
mean by civilization is
roughly the things like the the axioms
the assumptions the heuristics the
models the practices the institutions
that we humans use to solve problems and
to make our meet our needs so whether
this means things like go to college or
get a job at a company and get paid
money to buy food or go to a grocery
store to get food right these are all
the things that our civilization
produces to allow us to solve problems
and get our needs met and an insight and
I think a core thing for more and more
people to really grasp is that our
civilization toolkit this thing that has
gotten us so far this thing that has
produced seven and a half billion people
on a level of capacity and wealth and
well-being that's never been seen before
is itself the thing that is reached its
end it just can't solve the problems
that we're facing and by the way it's
also falling apart under its own terms
but that's a different conversation and
so what we have to do is we have to
figure out first how to unload that
toolkit unload our assumptions unload
the things that have worked so well and
get all the way down to the deep code
and rebuild something kind of from
scratch and we're gonna have to do this
very rapidly so this involves something
that we've never done before as a people
it's going to require a level of vision
it's going to acquire a level of
communion it's going to require a level
of peace that is I mean largely is
considered to be fiction or prophecy and
now it's not now it is in fact minimum
necessary requirements which is kind of
an interesting thing you know sometimes
I find myself sitting Daniel and I work
together in a business and sitting in
the room having a conversation about
business E things and I'll just reflect
and say gosh last night as having
conversations with people that it's
quite like Oh than the next seven years
our oceans will just be dead and that's
the clock and these are the things that
we're dealing with and we were talking
outside the Daniel wants to make sure
that as we're communicating that people
are left here with the sense of
empowerment and not a sense of panic or
fear and what I'd like to convey is a
sense of resolve
which is recognized that we must in fact
actually step in and that fear and panic
although they may be a very natural
response just aren't a useful response
okay so that's that's that part now I
think most what we're going to be
talking about is actually pretty
intellectual that is not to say that we
believe that the solution is in fact
even largely intellectual there was a
piece for the mind to play but in fact
some of the questions that came from
Facebook the basic answer is heart so I
think this is a great place to begin the
conversation
I guess publicly one concept that I'd
like to download before I hand off to
Daniel is a framework that a friend of
mine Dave Snowden not Ed Snowden but
Dave stone
introduced about 10 years ago for
thinking about the different kinds of
ordered systems that we find ourselves
in all right so you ready this is a very
intellectual framework but I think we
can do it quickly
the first kind of system is a simple
system and this is something like the
way a pendulum swings back and forth or
a game of tic-tac-toe where then the
phase space which is the the state the
set of available states in the system is
relatively small like the total number
of tic-tac-toe games and can fit on a
page it's not that many things and so
even a child can sit and observe the
system for a while get the whole thing
understand what to do and master it so
that's it's a simple system a
complicated system is the sort of thing
that we humans our civilization is very
very good at building and these are
things like say the Boeing 777 or the
national energy grid or interstate
highway system things that are extremely
large face this is a whole bunch of
states the system is able to handle so
much more that no person can ever really
grasp them in their entirety you could
never master them but if you spend
enough time with them you can build up
an expertise and understand what the
states are and how they interact and if
you get a crew of people who are all
experts in the system you can begin to
manage it and that idea this notion of
becoming experts and managing
complicated systems is a kind of a
succinctly of framing what we do what
our civilization is extraordinarily
good at doing now the thing about
complicated systems that distinguishes
them from complex systems as although
the phase space is very large it doesn't
change so once you've figured out the
Boeing 777 you can print out the whole
manual put it aside and look it up and
then and that's that in a complex system
things do change now it's interesting
about complex systems is on the one hand
it's only been about three or four
decades that we've even been thinking
about them seriously like the name isn't
even more than three decades old we're
just really beginning to get a handle on
what these things are and how they
operate and on the other hand things
like our bodies our minds or
relationships or ecology our economies
those are all complex systems which is
to say all the stuff we actually care
about is complex and a big part of the
game that we've been playing as people
for the past fifteen thousand years at
least has been trying to use complicated
stuff to manage complex stuff and this
generates a real problem you see in a
complex system things like causation is
are almost impossible to really figure
out you can't make predictions with
precision but exactly what your impact
is going to have on the system feedback
loops feed-forward loops emergent
properties new capacities that didn't
even exist evolution these are all
characteristics of complexity and one of
the big problems and in some sense a
nature of the the problem were facing is
that when you have a complicated system
trying to manage a complex system as the
complex system changes which is what
it's going to do the complicated system
has to become more complicated to deal
with the the failure modes and so it
gets more and more complicated and more
and more complicated until eventually
it's so complicated that you can't
manage it and then it has to do
something that Dave student calls takes
a journey through chaos and chaos is the
fourth kind of system and we don't like
chaos chaos is generally a very sad
place to be and we might even want to
say that we don't want to take a journey
through chaos but it seems unfortunately
rather unlikely we're going to be able
to do that because every single time a
truly complicated system has to adapt to
a complexity can't manage
the way that it breaks down is it
disorderly and it goes through chaos and
then you come back into authentic
complexity so it might be the case and
something to consider that our job right
now is twofold first is to figure out
how to position ourselves so that we can
in fact endure the chaos possibly you
can be anti fragile to the chaos and you
use the chaos to build something very
positive and then second to do what we
can now to envision what a future looks
like that embraces complexity
authentically and does not retain
complexity but worked with complexity
and build a civilization or whatever we
would want to call it it may be
something completely different that is
directly related to the natural dynamics
of complexity
okay so Jordan used the word anti
fragile which means resilient if we can
get the gain down a little bit but more
than just resilient it means that when
things come up that are going to be
deviations from the homeo dynamics of
that system it's not only going to not
break but it's going to be able to learn
from them and the system's gonna evolve
you mentioned that complex systems are
evolving so complicated systems are not
self-organizing right the 747 is a
designed externally design thing as
opposed to a self-organizing an emergent
thing that's another key distinction you
notice that our human civilization
systems are macro economic systems the
way we think about putting the
principles of them together our
governance systems especially our
infrastructure are complicated systems
but they interface with the complex
systems of ecology of human psyches of
social you know human social dynamics
and the behavioral dynamics of economies
and so it's important to get that our
built world or human built world is not
anti fragile it's not self-organizing
right and so it's it is fragile to
collapse and we've seen this if we look
at civilizations throughout history they
didn't all fare well right and it's
important to get that because since we
didn't go through Easter Island and we
didn't go through the collapse of most
of the things that were called
civilizations in the past and in our
life we haven't
to that at all we don't actually have an
experiential intuition for really
breaking down and so it seems like that
just couldn't really happen intuitively
because we haven't been exposed to it
intuition is conditioned by our
experience our intuition is not adequate
right our experiential intuition is not
adequate for the scope of what we face
this is a super important topic and so
when we look at Syria we see that their
complicated system right there their
governance system their infrastructure
has radically collapsed we see that it
was complex dynamics that led to the
collapse of that scenario and the lack
of ability to support life of the people
who are there lots of complex right
there were economic motives there were
all kinds of social and political
motives but there were also droughts
that were most likely the result of
climate change that led to subsistence
farmers not being able to grow food that
led to them coming into the cities that
led to resource collapse resource Wars
that then collapse a complicated systems
right this is complex system failure
creating breakdown of the complicated
systems that we depend upon so this is
when Jordans saying that our previous
toolkit isn't adequate more complicated
blueprints are not going to get us there
right that's one aspect I want to talk
about another part of our toolkit that
has to change which is our motivational
toolkit right not just our design
toolkit but our motivational toolkit
what we think of as you know the game
theoretic or the behavioral mechanics in
it so we've we can think about phases
that civilization has gone through many
people have brought up the point right
when Gandhi was asked what do you think
of Western civilization he said I think
it would be a good idea and it's
actually a meaningful point right
because he's saying it and and Jacque
fresco has famously said this many
people's as long as homelessness is okay
and you and you're gonna kind of focus
on other stuff and as long as killing
each other is a reasonable solution to
conflict resolution is it fair to call
that civilized yet or you know is it
fair to call it humanity isn't really
humane so maybe civilization and
humanity
are terms that we are aspiring to we
haven't got to yet and maybe the birth
of civilization a term actually
deserving of that is what is on the
other side of this chaos if we if we
navigate towards that so when we talk
about the history of civilization
usually we're talking about the history
of empire post agriculture right that's
usually the timeframe that we're talking
about and when we when we look at phases
right we'll call you know
hunter-gatherer tribes and then groups
of tribes and then fiefdoms and kingdoms
and movements towards nation-states
corporations globalism even though those
were fundamentally different
organizational dynamics for some in
group to win at a competitive game for
scarce resources against some other out
group they all had that in common they
were all playing win-lose games that was
fundamental to their game theory right
so in-group out-group fundamentally
zero-sum win lose game theoretic
dynamics so if you disagree with people
or you want the same resources that are
scarce and so you decide to kill each
other as a solution and you're dealing
with Spears
you'll kill some people but not
everybody and not the whole ecosystem if
you're gonna race to pull out the
unremovable resources from the ecosystem
fat faster but you are doing it with
access you'll damage some ecosystems but
not all right but as your tools are
going through exponential increases in
power in the capacity to affect the
world then the capacity to cause damage
will actually leads to a place where win
lose becomes lose lose right when when
you go from stone tools to guns to
missiles to weapons of mass destruction
there is no such thing as winning a war
at that level and so when lose attempt
becomes Omni lose-lose for everybody
right when you go towards racing towards
who can extract the dwindling resources
fast enough with the kinds of industrial
technology that allow us to extract them
so much faster than they can regenerate
that's Omni lose-lose
everybody so we're going through a shift
where we either have lose lose
motivational dynamics or Omni win-win
and there's no spaces in between we've
never had an omni win-win worldview
right we had win for everybody in our
civilization but usually not even that
it's like win for the ruling class and
the civilization at the cost of the
peasant classes that do all the work in
the labor force etc so what does it mean
to really recognize that the level at
which we can affect each other because
of exponential technology requires that
we take full consideration for making
sure that we're not externalizing harm
with that effect on the planet that
can't handle the externalization load
anymore so you know we use the term Omni
considerate and obviously we can't be
fully on the conserve but it's a
directional to our moving in the
direction of considering more so that
there is no externality gap right we can
say that the future of macroeconomics
one of the defining criteria has to be
that the incentive of every agent in the
system and that's every person or group
of people has to be aligned with the
well-being of every other agent and of
the Commons and any place where someone
is incentive to do something that
directly or indirectly causes harm
somewhere else you cannot prevent harm
that your incentive well a system that
meets that criteria looks like no system
of economics that we have ever had it's
not Marxism it's not socialism it's not
capitalism it's not a retrofit of any of
those systems either now notice that
exponential tech which means the the
ability to affect the world radically
more powerfully into it most people
don't have an intuition that can make
any sense of exponential curves of any
kind exponential curves where the next
phase in the iteration can have as much
change as the entire curve up to that
point what that means is that the way we
solve problems previously is becoming
more and more obsolete faster and faster
with more and more consequence this is
this is a big deal right this way we're
talking about a transition not just an
iteration
and so when we think about exponential
curves in the ability to affect things
where our tools give us more ability to
make better tools faster like we see
with Moore's Law and computing like we
see with biotech nanotech right all of
those areas as our ability to impact the
world is scaling up radically our choice
making for how to implement that power
effectively right to implement it Omni
considerately has to be scaling and
right now it's not even close so when
the first technology that was powerful
enough that had portended our ability to
take ourselves out the first existential
tech which was the bomb and you know
Einsteins insights it led to the bomb he
said famously it's painfully evident
that our technology is far surpassed our
humanity we have to fix that issue right
we have to make sure that we have
exponential increase in our choice
making capacity and you can you know
Jordan said it almost feels mythic right
like the coming of the end of an age and
the possible emergence of a new age
there it's reasonable right to think of
those metaphors and so if you think of
it in the mythic sense as people is
we're scaling towards having the power
of gods if we don't have the wisdom and
consideration and love of gods and that
power is inexorably self terminating
right so we have to move from
complicated system designed to actually
understanding complexity there's a as
one example of many of our frameworks of
problem solving having to change we also
have to move from thinking that we can
solve some of our problems independent
of or at the expense of others as a
reasonable approach that also has to
change and so where there were local
issues before when the people died on
Easter Island it didn't necessarily
impact everybody right we don't have
that scenario we have these radically
interconnected global issues where the
oceans dying is that everybody issue and
anyone contributing right any nation
contributing to those dynamics ends up
affecting all of us so you know Nations
made sense when the level at which we
affected things was a kind of a national
level and we could govern at the level
that we affect things but where we're
affecting things at a global level
we have to really govern and think of
that at that space right so the idea
that there can be collapsed somewhere
and we're unaffected by it and we get to
make it through that's also an obsolete
idea and on a very short timescale if
you look at the different groups that
are looking at catastrophic risk an
existential risk
there's variance and what the timescales
are but they're all profoundly shorter
than most of us think about on a daily
basis how many people here feel that
right feel the sense of imminent shift
right so when you have a system that
where some things are getting
exponentially better more powerful other
things are getting exponentially worse
so it doesn't mean the system is going
in either those directions it means it's
destabilizing and you're getting to the
end of that phase you're either gonna
get a phase shift down to a much lower
level of organization which looks like
things that none of us want or a phase
shift up discreetly to a fundamentally
different set of organizational and
motivational and and even identity
worldview dynamics so that's what we're
here to talk about and explore more
tonight some design principles so I'm
gonna pick up on a few of the themes
that that have been raised by my good
friends one of the themes that has been
raised as the notion of complexity and
in a way of thinking of things we can
actually say that these these concepts
have relationships to one another that
these themes come together when we're
looking at complexity how do we deal
with complexity what is the tools that
we use to deal with complexity well
there's two other concepts that come to
mind one of them is simplicity and the
other is clarity these three concepts
always occur together they don't ever
occur separately where there is
something that is complex there's also
something else that is simple and there
is also something else that is clear so
the idea isn't to try to reduce
complexity into some state of simplicity
or to try to see it only through the
terms of something which is simple but
to actually use the tool of clarity to
be able to deal with complexity so and
if
fact what I'm gonna try to do is I'm
gonna try to be really clear about some
of the ideas that that have come forward
that we have about what sort of toolkit
can we bring to bear on the kinds of
problems that are facing us we know that
the solutions that have been brought
forward to create the civilization that
we're now in are no longer adequate for
dealing with the problem and when we try
to even identify what the problem is we
recognize that like life itself it's
very complex so the effort is
essentially to try to bring a kind of
clarity to the process what is the
essence of what is going on how do we
how do we understand it how do we relate
to it what ways can we influence or be
influenced by it and so when we're
looking at design when we're trying to
think about okay we're in a position of
having these conversations about choices
about the choices we make individually
about the choices we make collectively
as a community as a choices we make
collectively as a nation or as a globe
and so in effect a lot of the exercise
comes down to what are the principles of
effective choice how do we choose
together how do we align ourselves so
that the choices that we're making are
good choices and what does it mean to
make a good choice how would we know it
how would we recognize it how would we
understand whether the design that we're
proposing to solve a particular problem
is actually a good design it's something
that would create a solution that is
enduring that is anti fragile that would
in effect create a state of health
create a state of thriving we want to
use whatever choices we make
individually to try to move the society
that we're in the culture that we're in
into a phase transition that is in a
sense a healthier way of being and to do
that we would want to of course have
some idea of what health is so that we
can recognize it we would want to
appreciate the kinds of dynamics that
create systems that that actually have a
sense of vitality to them that we would
want to be a part of because we
recognize that it's good for our own
lives for our family for the quality of
life that we know we want to increase
that but to know how to do that in a way
that's balanced in a way that is
essentially Omni considerate well that's
complicated problem and in order for us
to to develop the tools to do these kind
of things in order to have designs that
are essentially good designs well you
need to even think about the notion of
how design works what kind of designs
are actually going to be effective in
this scenario and which ones will not be
nature has been of course a very good
example for a design process evolution
has in a sense resulted in the
complexity and the world did we know in
a lot of the solutions that were aware
of have been arrived by a process of
evolution evolution as a design
methodology although it is somewhat
unconscious tends to be very thorough
when we're looking at design for
something of a biological nature like
considering just the eyeball right just
this one organ that we have it isn't
that it just solves one problem figuring
out a way to see what's in the world's
and have that information be something
that we can respond to them it actually
solves a whole constellation of
different problems simultaneously it has
to be something which is possible to
grow when you're you know born you don't
have an eye and then when you basically
arrive on this planet you have a
functioning organ it had to go from a
state of not being to a state of being
there needed to be some way for the the
organic systems to essentially emerge
with this structure this organism it has
to in effect be self-healing you know if
I get a piece of grit where I scratch it
or something you know bumps it or I have
something go wrong that there's a
there's an automatic mechanism that it
uses to essentially repair itself how
many of your cameras will repair
themselves you drop a cell phone and it
cracks it's not going to heal it's just
going to stay cracked and in a sense the
kind of the kind of evolutionary process
that has resulted in the design of this
marvelous piece of technology that in a
lot of ways exceeds anything that we can
build today has not just optimized for
one particular aspect but is essentially
solving a whole constellation of
problems simultaneously so when we're
looking at civilization design how to in
effect recreate what we mean by the very
notion of civilize what is the essence
of the problem we're actually trying to
solve it's not something that we're
going to address by optimizing for any
single particular function
in fact even the notion of optimization
itself is something of a problem we
don't get to the kinds of solutions that
we need by optimizing for any single
metric or even any finite set of metrics
we need to in a sense know what are the
principles what are the characteristics
that a good solution needs to have when
I'm trying to make decisions I'm not
necessarily and go through some sort of
calculus equation to figure out whether
or not it's a good decision I'm gonna
say does it have these characteristics
does it in a sense meet the minimum
necessary and sufficient criteria in
order for it to actually be a solution
in the space that it's supposed to be a
part of I'll give you an example so I I
do a lot of product design I have a
company and we make things and we sell
them to the commercial market to the end
consumers really and you know a lot of
people that approach me and say hey I
have this great idea I want to I want to
make this thing and I want to sell it to
people and so on and so forth and you
know I look at it and and you know we
have a conversation and I ask a few
questions I ask okay so you know do we
have the materials can we can we source
the stuff that this thing is made of can
we build the tools that that that are
necessary to make this thing can we
train the people to to use the tools to
make the product can we afford to have
you know can we pay people to do that
has anybody thought about the
instructions that are that are necessary
to be read by the person that's going to
use this thing is there an idea of how
you're going to present it to the market
do you know who the beneficiary of this
work is do you understand all of the the
kinds of relationships that are going to
evolve in the marketplace and how it's
going to change the market have you
accounted for what happens with the
product after a person's done using it
where does it eventually go in the
environment does it come back to the
manufacturer and you recycle it somehow
or another does it end up in a landfill
you know when we look at things like
pollution there's a sort of this
realization that pollution happens the
instant that something is made it's not
you know sometime later on when it ends
up in the landfill as soon as we combine
something that nature has no way of
taking it apart we've already become
part of the problem so in effect we need
to think about a much broader set of
questions a much broader set of of ideas
a much broader set of issues and
characteristics
in order for us to essentially identify
to recognize that we are even thinking
about this an appropriate way are we
even asking the right questions and how
would we know so in a lot of ways the
the details that we're trying to get to
the things that that are essentially
really important how do we organize
ourselves into communities of people
that can collectively influence some of
the situations that are affecting all of
us what does it mean for us to
essentially align our choices as agents
into a way that actually makes sense
what does that mean when we think about
the notion of civilization in a lot of
ways it comes down to a kind of
conversation when I think of
civilization I think of people's
capacity their availability to talk to
one another and the level and quality of
the conversations that are that are
having it's not you know our current
culture has gotten very enamored with
this so-called broadcast process Here I
am you know giving this presentation and
and in effect you know I'd like to
actually rather than speaking at you to
be having a conversation with you right
but in effect where we've gotten so used
to this method of providing information
in some sort of bulk account and that
we've in effect had this this sort of
method of communicating that is
essentially a top-down way of thinking
and we've gotten very used to design
processes that are very top-down design
process you know we have a problem we
want to solve we figure out a way to
solve that particular problem and then
we work out all the details and then we
you know we deliver right sort of a
waterfall lifecycle design what we
really need in this particular point is
a kind of design a kind of conversation
there rather than being from some sort
of central single monolithic point of
view has in a sense a kind of diffused
integration that has a kind of organic
quality to it we don't have the time to
wait for evolution to figure this out
and given some of the powers and
capacities that we have developed
technologically we uneffective have
entered into the responsibility of being
responsible for our own evolution being
responsible for our own design
so thinking about design questions in a
way that's neither top-down which is
maybe accurate but not precise enough or
bottom-up which may be really really
precise but takes a long time we find
ourselves in a situation where we need
to come up with design capabilities
design characteristics that have the
rapidity of top-down but the
effectiveness of bottom-up and so in a
sense our exercise is essentially to
develop a set of tools to develop a set
of conversations to set the set of
intelligence building apparatus that
allows us to deal with complexity in a
profoundly clear way so that's what this
conversation is about tonight so before
we get to the questions and answers I
just wanted to bring two more things one
is a strategic framework for how at
least I go about thinking about what I
want to do and how I want to participate
in this thing because I have certainly
noticed over the past couple of decades
that different people have different
proclivities their different preferences
they have different kinds of things that
they're attracted to and things that are
not interested in at all and so there's
no one Pro try this every single person
here is fully responsible for doing
exactly what is theirs to do in this
thing but it seems like there are three
basic categories that things are pulling
apart into and they're almost temporal
so the first category is is the category
of the urgent there are things that are
urgent things that we must not let
happen over the next couple of years and
those aren't too hard to guess and
unfortunately we're getting off the
close to them things like say a nuclear
war among the great powers would be the
sort of thing that we would must avoid
over the next couple of years and
there's a number actually of things that
are absolutely urgent and must be
avoided or in fact must it must happen
over the next several years two three
four years and
if you're the kind of person who has the
energy and commitment and ability to
sacrifice to address those kinds of
things that's a good place to go but if
you are don't waste your time on things
that require 15 years of planning
it's just a very those things are out of
match the second category is a category
or a lot of folks are spending time on
right now and this is in the time frame
maybe anchored on say seven years or 15
years somewhere in there depending on
how things play out and I consider this
to the period of transition and this is
the period where we do our absolute
level best to squeeze a couple more
years out of the current civilization
model to hold us as we engineer the
transition so when we land it's a soft
landing and so something likes a
universal basic income which is was a
question that it was asked and is
something that's getting more and more
conscious now is in that category it's
not post transition it's transitional if
it works it will get us to the next step
but it will not be the next step itself
and then the third stage is that is the
stage that Forrest was talking about the
post transitional stage and that's
extremely difficult this is the sort of
thing that to be resilient to
exponential technology is going to
require a level of capability a level of
precision a level of design that we we
can barely name and we haven't really
fully figured out how to embody yet and
it's gonna take years
all right so heart in some sense if
you're in the first two categories your
job is to buy time so the people who are
prepared to try to do the stuff at the
post transition framework can get those
things in place so we're actually have a
good thing to land on and if you're a
visionary who can input put names
against those things to seek out the
people who are who are equipped to be
able to take that vision and bring it
into reality and so that's one piece of
material that I hope is helpful to
people in thinking how to apply
themselves the other is the hopeful side
of this conversation and I had a
conversation with our friend Brett I
think maybe yesterday
about a dynamic that's going on a number
of different places and this group is
certainly part of that which is
when he will call the shamanic path and
he's an evolutionary theorist and he put
it this way he said human beings
actually tend to operate in two modes
when things are going well or actually
if things are going even marginally okay
we tend to just kind of like stay where
we are and run the code that we've
already written and we like that that's
really safe because change is generally
a very bad thing but when things are
clearly not doing well then we actually
have to shift into a different mode and
we have to call up the shamanic energy
you know people sitting around the fire
and talking about things people dancing
ecstatically people taking drugs to be
able to think differently because as
individuals we really can't think we do
not think as individuals we think as
groups we think as groups in
conversation with each other as forrest
is saying really learning the art of
coming together in groups they can have
these conversations and rebirthing are
actually calling out in ourselves the
shamanic energy to be able to actually
have the kind of consciousness necessary
to do the things we're talking about is
the thing the thing to be done and the
good news is is that even though we have
only grown up in a time frame where
these sorts of things haven't happened
in our memory we are the the ancestors
and the descendants of people who have
had that time frame so it's in us to do
it and I imagine most people here are
actually feeling it and have faults for
quite some time all the way down at the
cellular level
so it's tuning into that and figuring
how to recover that thing I think is
also a big piece of the solution
all right so we've got some questions
that have come in both online prior to
this event as well as all of you I hope
have been writing questions as as these
gentlemen have been sharing and we're
gonna pass around a box in about five
minutes to collect your questions and
then they're going to be ordered and
prioritized as best as possible and and
shared so please if you haven't already
if you have a burning question that you
would think would be relevant to a large
audience please jot it down and the box
will go around in about five minutes in
the meantime we've got some great ones
that have come in online and let's start
right here
so there it is how can I most
effectively evaluate and calibrate my
own truth detection process how can I as
objectively as possible find out if a
problem is real or probably real versus
an overreaction or a misperception about
collective reality or reality itself
first if you have found yourself
responding to the environment let's say
for example you're among the very large
number of people who responded to the
2016 election with some mixture of anger
or fear stop those emotions are very
effective at driving action they're
extremely poor at finding truth so relax
slow down
and I'm not saying slow down in the face
of danger because there is danger but as
our friends in the Marines say slow is
smooth and smooth is fast
becomes smooth so first if you're not
smooth become smooth nothing else can be
good until you are smooth this is very
important right now
second Forrest mentioned an unfortunate
model that we found ourselves trained
into largely from birth if you've been
watching television certainly since you
got to went to school which is too
get into a mode of broadcast of being
the recipient of information that comes
from people who you've never met and is
broadcast out to a very large number of
people that is broadly untrustworthy no
matter what the origin source is if it
is broadcast it is broadly untrustworthy
which means that you can listen to it
but you're gonna have to do a lot of
work to make any sense out of it at all
I spent about the last year now
receiving information from hundreds of
descriptors that I painstakingly curate
to make sure they are completely
separate from each other and honestly I
can't make sense of what's going on
right now very well so it's very
unlikely if you're getting news from
three or four sources that you're going
to be able to actually use that to make
sense of what you in particular should
be doing right
I mean you may be able to get really
angry about something's going on nowhere
near you but that doesn't help you
so the key is in fact this thing that
Forrest was talking about this the way
we're going to do this is we're going to
have to begin engaging in conversations
with people we have to get in honestly
we're in a situation where we we
actually have the ability to engage in
conversations with people all over the
world
and we can find them and talk with them
and share with them authentically and
listen to what it is that they're
actually trying to express regardless of
what their words sound like to us and
relearn the art of actually creating
these new forms of collective
consciousness and that may sound
superficial but it is absolutely the
opposite of superficial it is hard to do
and people are crazy
I mean it's nuts out there and and
people also have crazy ideas like we use
words to meet all kinds of weird things
so it's beginning to build from the
bottom up it is actually the thing that
we're doing so it's not that we're
trying to find the truth so that we can
figure out the next thing to do it is
the thing we are doing and having the
ability to in yourself be able to listen
to things that make you respond
emotional or make no sense to your mind
learn how to ask questions how to listen
to enter into dialogue how to seek out
and find the people who have the thing
that you need to share how to share what
it is yours
right now I mean that's a really
interesting challenge how do you not
just run the response or persona tells
you gets people to do this you want
them to do how do you actually share
what is actually yours that you were
here to give that is a fundamental
lesson to learn and so that notion by
direction it being able to do that that
is my answer that question picking up on
what Jordan said best source of
information is people you know in other
words rather than trying to get
information from news sources of people
you don't know you don't know the filter
that that information is coming through
right anything that's a broadcast
communication anything that's
essentially a one-to-many communication
transit transaction and when I say many
I mean like thousands or more you're
going to have essentially a conflict of
motivation that is essentially there's a
there's a commoditization of attention
and time your heart beats right that
irreplaceable
moments in your life which will never be
repeated again okay so in effect what
you what you what you first want to sort
of keep in mind is is that we don't make
sense of anything by ourselves we make
sense of things in the community of
people that we know and trust and in
effect you know by knowing the person
that is in a sense has in their
awareness that you're interested in this
particular topic or that they they have
a way of thinking about it that is very
clear that they in a sense become a
resource for you to know what that
information actually means in context
right to have someone be able to say
here's my perspective on it but you know
the kind of perspectives that they have
gives you a lot more information a lot
more sense making capacity than
receiving information from any anonymous
source so the kinds of things that we
naturally do we we hang out with our
friends
and we have conversations I'm suggesting
we do that a lot more and that we do it
a lot more deliberately and that we do
it with the kind of intention that is
the specific intention of seeking
insight that we in effect are trying to
see through the perspective of another
individual so that we can combine it
with our own perspective and have a
greater depth a greater dimensionality
of perception
and what otherwise be possible right we
have to two of these organs we have two
of these organs in fact we have this
capacity to take the information that we
see in each of these eyes and synthesize
it together to perceive three dimensions
where any single organ by itself would
only see two and this is a technology
this is actually a very powerful
technology if I wanted to build a radio
telescope that was bigger than the size
of the planet I take the signal that is
received at you know the middle of
summer and then I wait six months and I
take the signal that is received in the
middle of winter and I combine them in a
certain way and I get the effect as if I
had built something that was the size of
the orbit of the earth as an amazing
amazing result it's like this this
enormous multiplicative effect when we
seek out diverse opinions diverse people
you don't want to just talk to people
that you know but you also want to talk
to people that are interesting then in a
sense you have a kind of intuition that
something they say may combine in an
interesting way was something that did
you would say to them and that through
that sharing through that mutual
experience that you will each perceive
the world in a way that is more genuine
more depth and that's what we mean to
make sense of something to in a sense
get to the point where we see into it to
have insight is to see into so put your
cell phones away get together for dinner
and talk about some real right I
mean that's basically what it boils down
to and remember what you remember what
insights you have write it down you know
put it put it in some sort of notebook
or something and then the next
conversation the next dinner party that
you have bring out the best of the best
of what you have in a sense come to
insights for and synthesize that to a
deeper level the more you go through
this process the easier it is and the
more insights that you gain the more
insights that we have into the kind of
designs and the solutions that will
constitute Civilization 2.0 add to what
these guys said because this might be
the most important question of the night
just to underscore the importance
do we know what's happening at Fukushima
really or how long we have for coral
reefs before we have to do what right
how do we navigate how do we do
collective choice making when we don't
have collective sense making how do we
prioritize it like this is Jordan has
written extensively about this this is a
core existential civilization issue and
individually we take in information we
process it and we act on it but we're
we're all inter affecting each other and
we're dealing with macro phenomena we
have to be collectively taking in
information right treating each other as
sensors and collectively processing it
and being able to collectively act on it
it is by definition the case that all
perspectives on reality are going to be
a reduction of reality they're gonna
have blind spots that are unavoidable
the only way you start to address them
is having more perspectives and then the
ability to start to integrate and
synthesize those of course was saying
get together and talk to people and both
of them were saying get together and
talk to people that one of the keys was
people who have different perspectives
and different data different Intel
because you know how many people were
really surprised by the Trump election
who were talking to people about
politics that all were in the same
misinformation bubble that they were in
right and because they stayed within a
worldview protected in group
misinformation bubble the world they
thought existed in the world that
actually existed were really radically
different and so a couple things I would
add is want to know what the world
actually is rather than want to
reinforce your ideas about it because if
your ideas about it are off they will be
maladaptive so want to get perspective
that is different than and even
challenging to the current way that you
see things critical one step deeper than
that is separate your identity from your
worldview
right so that your sense of security
emotionally and your sense of certainty
about certain facts are decoupled
because to the degree that your ability
to not freak out is because you're
fairly sure about something you will not
take alternate opinions on that
alternate perspectives even if it's
wrong and so the ability to have some
sense of inability to not freak out that
is decoupled from being fairly certain
about things is actually really
important conversations that I've had
with these two gentlemen particularly is
that I know that when they say something
that they've thought about it carefully
and so as a result I can I can put aside
whatever beliefs I have and whatever
reactions I might be experiencing or
whatever my my ideas or thoughts or
opinions might be and say okay I really
want to know what this person is
thinking I want to understand how they
are perceiving the world because
whatever it is that they're saying it
means something and and so in effect a
lot of the conversations are really
based upon this idea that we believe
that the other person is saying
something that is meaningful it's
important so in effect we want to engage
that aspect as the essence what is
important ask that question what's
important for you right now what's
important in this conversation what is
important for us to say to one another
so that we each have a more
comprehensive view of what reality
actually is this whole thing about
having opinions and perceptions and such
like that there is a always going to be
this filtering process nature in a
census is going to be represented to us
through the filters of our perceptions
and our biases in effect we need to get
skilled at knowing what our biases are
and working around them uncovering the
blind spots seeing around the corner of
things or behind you
in effect we are at a civilization level
trying to uncover and to compensate for
sociological blind spots things that are
blind spots had an even bigger scale but
in order to do that we have to develop
some new skills we have to develop some
listening skills and listening skills in
the census what is the essence of what's
being said here what is truly important
what does this actually mean what are
the implications of this and so in
effect when we start to to really codify
our communication process on this basis
when we start to think about things in
the sense of okay I want to get to the
essence of this so that I understand it
really as it is as it actually is not as
I would have it be but as it in a sense
needs to be responded to you know when
things are going wrong the first
principle I heard in management class or
training or whatever was stop look see
and tell the truth this goes back to
what Jordan was talking about when he
said first thing you want to do is slow
down in order to get more insight and
more depth you want to slow down and
sink into the truth sink into the
feelings of what your nervous system is
actually telling you there are enormous
number of tools that we have built-in
for every blind spot there are a couple
of - winnings - things that are good and
for everything that's good there's
actually a couple of blind spots so we
need to know how to navigate this the
way that we know that the way that we
navigate through the minefield of what's
possible this is slow down you don't go
running through a minefield that tends
to get you blown up so go slow so forest
Daniel Jordan what I'm hearing you say
is one the importance of these sense
making tools both as a collective as
well as individuals and it's interesting
how that as a process leads to empathy
it leaves who more deeply understanding
the other this next question is about
building new models that make old models
obsolete without creating absolute chaos
is that possible
so how I think I can take that one so
when we're looking at large system
design you know like let's say you have
a an operating system you know it's a
very complicated piece of software and
for some reason or other then you need
to change it and you want to make sure
that you actually have a computer that
continues to work because you meet it
you know to do things while these
changes are going on it is possible to
do that it's a technique called
refactoring where you basically are
partitioning the source code and you're
working with you know segments of it but
you're keeping the whole system
operational and rerouting signals across
the path that you're trying to fix so it
is possible to do this but it takes an
awful lot of skill right if you are
essentially trying to recreate an
operating system of course the easy way
to do is to trash the old one and start
from scratch and create the new one but
oftentimes this isn't actually a very
good idea because what happens is is
that it throws out the baby with the
bathwater all of the problems that the
old system actually effectively was a
solution for I have to be addressed
again from scratch and half the time we
don't even know what those problems are
what those solutions actually you know
what the techniques of solving those
problems actually were so our new system
may not actually be an improvement it
might solve this set of problems over
here but all these things that used to
work are broken so in effect when we're
looking at system design part of the
things that we want to do and we're
we're trying to morph a large
complicated system is to first of all
try to you know look at the picture of
what its functionality actually is what
problems does it actually solve what are
the assumptions that were made that may
be different now or what are the
assumptions that were made that are
still true that we need to in a sense
continue to uphold you have clarity
about those kinds of things then you can
start replacing components one at a time
or you could start basically going
through the system and using the
components of the old one to build a new
one having a clearer sense of what a
successful architecture looks like means
that to some extent you understood the
old architecture and understood it well
enough to understand what problems it
was a solution for and what things it
was not a solution for so that when
you're designing the new thing you're in
a sense
encompassing and incorporating all of
the learning and all of the knowledge of
the thousands of programmers that came
before you the answer to the second
question depends upon how good we are
the first question right our ability to
understand the nature of the problems
well enough one force was describing how
many things and I've all simultaneously
optimizing for one of the challenges
with the issues is that when we get
scared and we want to go fast and we
don't understand the problem space well
enough in addressing some of it we might
be externalizing issues and even more
problematic way and so we can see like
getting scared about climate change and
so we need we need to address
temperature one metric right temperature
is a big metric coral that's the first
one for them so geoengineering in a way
that has potentially huge externality
load and doesn't address any of the
causal dynamics where there actually are
solutions that address the causal
dynamics is the kind of thing that
happens if you don't sense make well
enough and then you're in a rush right
to get through so it's it's critical to
actually keep coming back to that right
a problem well understood is half solved
in engineering aphorism that more deeply
we can understand that the better
knowing what questions ask a couple more
things on so the question was based off
of the the Bucky fuller quote we don't
try and fight the existing system but
build new ones that are fundamentally
more adequate meet the needs better that
obsolete the old system and they just
become then a strange attractor right
because they're they're more selective
so that's the topic of prototyping right
civilization prototyping this is one of
the critical things that has to happen
that with people in here who are focused
on eco villages and intentional
communities all the way up to city
scales right and what would be the
minimum viable scale to start
prototyping a different economy a
different governance of different
materials economy a different set of
social dynamics and coherence and that's
the kind of get a sense of what is
actually potentially viable in in real
instance
and then to the extent that it is
successful model be able to reverse
engineer that becoming more wide you
know then there's also the forward
engineering of how do we take
civilization wide dynamics that we can
make iterative shifts on that move the
whole system forward and one of the key
dynamics is move it forward towards more
health in a way that increases our
capacity right that up regulates our
collective capacity to answer that
question better in the next iteration
historically whenever we go through a
major transition there are two failure
conditions that lead thing lead to
things being very bad the first has to
do with the way the elites relate to the
transition so think about for example
the American Revolution the French
Revolution and the collapse the Roman
Empire in each of those characteristics
the elites related to them transition
very differently in the collapse of the
Roman Empire the elites simply refused
to allow a transition to occur until the
mismatch between their system and the
complexity gotten so high that it did in
fact go to what I would consider to be a
good representation of absolute chaos we
need to avoid that like the plague and
so finding ways to get some portion of
our elites to be able to have a
consciousness of the necessity of being
deliberate about change is extremely
important but if you think about the
American Revolution at least in the
United States along the coast in the
colonies a pretty sizable function of
elites who we now know as the founding
fathers were willing to step into and
take leadership in making that change
happen
now the other failure condition comes
from the fact at the end of the day
we're all monkeys
we're primates right we've gotten pretty
good at not killing each other in this
room and staring and being quiet because
we've trained really hard at doing that
but as civilization starts to break down
we go right back to being Apes and the
way that apes don't freak out is when
some of the Apes seem to know what the
is going on and they don't freak
out alright so when things go crazy
you're gonna see people gonna start
looking around if I write who
to have their act together have your act
together it's the emergent leaders is
the second piece right the people who
have done the work to be able to hold
fast and not panic when things begin to
break apart that other people will look
to and say where is the anchor what's
going on here and if we have enough of
those people embedded in what's
happening even as things fall down they
don't go to absolute chaos it's actually
very interesting it's not an objective
function we've seen experiences where
monetary systems have completely
vaporized people have had a hard time
eating there's been fighting didn't go
to absolute chaos because something held
the fabric together right people certain
emergent leaders are willing to step up
and say no we're still gonna be
civilized we're still gonna hold this
thing together that's the other answer
to it so the the architecture and the
mechanics and the thinking in the
process all very true but at the
foundation if you want to keep these
monkeys from tearing each other apart
you know be the person you want to be
completing up the next question awesome
Jordan so so let's get into the how of
that so this next question is how can we
realign everyone's sense of purpose
towards the well-being of all and away
from the self-interest of the market
economies so that we actually
wholeheartedly cooperate and even
innovate with such transitions how do we
get there as humans
the answer is necessarily iterative one
of the things there's there's a
dialectic of different things that
you're hearing in the group which is hey
things are more eminently collapsing
then you're aware of on a day-to-day
basis when you're thinking about
cleaning the house and paying the bills
etc so there's an urgency in that at the
same time we're hearing don't react too
fast with urgency and slow down what
that means is a shift of attention from
other less critical stuff to the topics
that are actually at hand because you
get that they're real I know how many
people have watched the videos of
Richard Fineman talking about space but
one of the things he does is beautiful
is
he's like when you think about the vast
distances of space and you think about
the number of stars that we talk about
like really think about and it's really
there it's hard for us on planet to
think about four hundred billion stars
in our galaxy it's not just hard it's
actually impossible but to the degree
that you try and then that's one tiny
galaxy to the degree that you try you're
being expands it's hard for us to think
about the well-being of everything in
our personal choice consideration set
and it's hard for us to get that the
civilization that we have known and that
the people we've respected have known is
coming to an end and that the solutions
aren't within that wisdom set it's
actually super hard to get that but you
can write as you start to as you start
to think about it you can actually get
oh wait exponential growth materials
economy extracting resources faster than
they replenish find a planet that just
actually doesn't enduringly work that's
a fairly simple math right you can start
to educate about those things and maybe
we don't know exactly what the
timeframes are but that this current
civilization set is shifting and se-ra
if I take that seriously if I really
take that seriously what do I do
differently well I'm gonna allocate more
time to getting more educated I'm gonna
develop my thinking and sense making
frameworks one of the things that we
didn't speak to earlier while we're
talking to people and when Forrest said
he takes seriously when Jordan or I say
something cuz we've thought about it
doesn't mean he agrees with all of it
right and it doesn't mean that he
rejects all of it means he has an
ability to have analytic thinking and
really critical thinking and parse is
this true is that not true how do we
know those are skills that are
developable that everybody has to
develop and then synthetic thinking well
that seems true and it seems quite
different than another truth how do
those actually fit together right so the
ability for analysis and synthesis
there's more than that that's necessary
but developing those frameworks and
putting data into those frameworks and
putting more time into the entire thing
but so how do we develop the care right
if you really think about and get that
your own success and the success of your
family is not insurer
independent of the success of the whole
if you get that that is true in the
timeframe of your life in your
children's life and in trying to ensure
their success independent of the success
of the whole it will fail yeah no can
you say that once more it's a really
important point that trying to ensure
our own individual success independent
of or even at the expense of the success
of others of the whole is not a viable
strategy and yet it was something that
seemed viable for a very long time and
so it's easy to kind of fall back on
that intuition but to get that it's a
fundamentally different time so so
people can get that intellectually but
how do you get them to be that
I'm gonna give time to think by throwing
something out that's part of the
conversation I mean didn't I mention
that this notion of win-lose was seemed
like a viable strategy for a very long
period of time I'm actually gonna make a
stronger statement that for effectively
all of evolutionary history up until
like a couple weeks ago it was by far
the best strategy it was the absolute
best strategy if you didn't do that you
were going to be selected against and
somebody else's children are going to be
the children who populated the world
it's really important to keep that in
mind like evolution really really really
wants us to struggle with other things
to survive but now we're in a situation
where things are changing so the the
magnitude this changes not just in the
sense that our civilization is
collapsing alright the other side is
well number Daniel mentioned that we're
reaching a point where there's going to
be a pivot and it's not they're going to
go up or down and if it goes down it
goes way down if it goes up it goes way
up and the people who talk about
abundance aren't wrong we actually have
created so much capacity that the kinds
of things that we have been struggling
over for hundreds of thousands of years
are no longer meaningful and so for
example you guys are I assume reasonably
familiar with this notion of
technological unemployment it's also
getting a lot of press in the Bay Area
and places like that but things like
self-driving cars are gonna unemploy 1.5
million people in the next decade and
that robots are gonna take everybody's
jobs now if you're on the scarcity
mindset that's very scary and being
unemployed is very bad
but if you flip it around what that
means is that we don't actually need
people to work that much anymore in fact
in some sense in the next 20 years but
do our things right nobody needs to work
anymore and we actually have to figure
out how to apply ourselves to something
completely different so we're in the
process again of watching this old
structure begin to fall apart and as
Dana said it's going to be iterative
right things like universal basic income
or a nice transitionary piece and there
will be other pieces as well that will
begin to buffer the feeling of scarcity
in a way that begins to allow people to
have actual
real freedom to not to have to feel like
they have to go out and fight you know
dog and dog and meats dog inside the
workplace to survive and then in the
meantime we're in the process of trying
to figure out how to build structures
that are designed for abundance which is
a very different thing I mean abundance
is a completely different framework of
how we go about doing things by the way
it's non-trivial you know purpose for
example is a big problem if you think
about it right now we have this really
night mat nice mesh where you work to
survive they glue together all right if
I pull that apart and I make it okay
well you don't have to work and you can
still survive where's purpose fit into
this most people get their sense of
purpose by being valuable to other
people by doing their job and creating
something in the world but if you're no
longer working and you're still
surviving that's actually terrible that
will destroy things if you don't have
some way of actually generating purpose
in different mechanism so there's
problems ining post-transition designing
for abundance is a spiritual it's a
psychological it's an economic it's a
technological process it is another way
of saying the new toolkit that were
trying to build some out there was
someone helpful so so Jordan used the
word whoa Jordan used the word purpose
and I think it was an entirely
appropriate choice there is these three
concepts purpose value and meaning and
those again are three things that go
together but are distinct right they are
three concepts that we tend to conflate
a lot when we talk about how do we
create an economy we're thinking about
value systems we're thinking about money
as a value system or you know an
exchange medium of some sort or another
right whereas when we're talking about
you know jobs and and you know what is
our function in life what do we do you
know you come to a party and you ask
okay well what do you do what's your job
and when we move into a situation that's
a post-scarcity economy we're looking at
an abundance economy of some sort or
another the usual ways of thinking of
defining our lives in terms of purpose
or in terms of value just aren't going
to work because it's not going to be
about that it's gonna be about the
meaningfulness of life meaningfulness
is deeper than value or purpose the
notions of value and purpose are
relative to the notion of meaningfulness
so if we're going to in a sense come to
you know some sort of alignment where
we're basically saying okay how do we as
individual people move beyond this
economic actor model where we're
basically having some sort of exchange
medium and that this exchange process is
how we create survival how we create
some sort of you know thing that is
essentially providing food and shelter
and all the rest of that stuff if we
come up with a way of using our
technology that manages to provide food
for every living person on this planet
which we actually have or technology
that allows us to provide shelter for
everybody which we actually also have
that really it becomes a question of
thinking about it differently right we
in a sense incorporate a kind of
non-economic foundation into creating
choice alignment and how do we do that
well we don't do it by trying to have a
purpose for everybody that we know we're
thinking in terms of how much of a
dollar value each person has you know
how much does your net worth isn't a
very meaningful conversation but on the
other hand you're talking about life
experiences or what's important to you
right now or what sort of insights that
you've had from an experience that you
had last week those are the things that
create true connections and in effect if
we're going to move into an economy of
essentially some sort of post scarcity
sort of situation it's going to be based
on a meaningfulness principle rather
than on a purpose principle or a value
principle and this is a key concept this
is something I believe to be a necessary
aspect of how to think about this sue
mentioned phases there's a transition
that we're in and there's urgent stuff
that allows us to keep figuring stuff
out there's a transition there's a post
transition the transition phase is
fundamentally different than the phase
that's transitioning from and to is a
key insight will maybe get to that more
later but to answer this question of how
do we increase the connectedness of the
sense of self and the sense of reality
and increase
CAIR awareness etc how do we do that
we said it was going to be iterative so
one design criteria is that for the in
the post transition phase that actually
has to be everybody and we mentioned
antifragility in the presence of
exponential technology we can't actually
put exponential technology back in the
bag that that's just an inexorable thing
that those capacities are there now when
you think about someone who you know we
see goes and does a mass shooting that
seemed kind of unprovoked if they have
the access to a gun and especially say
an automatic gun they can do more damage
in that process than if they have the
access to just a knife right and so now
as we take exponential technology where
you think about the first really
catastrophic technologies we had very
few people could have access to like
nuclear weapons as you move into
decentralized exponential tech and we're
very small numbers of people can have
really catastrophic actions the Omni
consideration and choice making has to
be universal not just some people
because there's no longer ruling class
that then has all the power and everyone
else who doesn't and so that's part of
the post transition design criteria and
it's a really deep big deal criteria to
think about so for instance most the
time that person who goes into the mass
shooting the neighbors say we didn't
really know them right they were quiet
they kept to themselves they were a
shut-in and so they could be developing
in their loneliness in their
psychopathology with nobody noticing it
that doesn't work right in the future so
how do we move to connected enough
civilizations that everyone is is
actually connected to other humans
meaningfully that others are connected
to them those are going to be key design
criteria but while we say everyone
Romney considered as part of post
transition it doesn't take everyone for
us to get there right this is the
iterative it takes some people building
capacities that start to change game
theory dynamics it's so you know the
person who goes and kills a whale on a
fishing boat because that whales worth
hundreds of
thousands of dollars or a million
dollars dead and alive it's not worth
anything it doesn't necessarily mean
that they are whale hating hating beings
right it might doesn't even mean that
they actually feel okay with it it means
that there's a game theory that doesn't
have everyone's incentive and everything
else is well being aligned and they
don't know how to feed their kids
otherwise right or they don't know how
to get ahead in whatever set of dynamics
so can you have those game theoretic
dynamics at scale and have everyone get
there No
so how do we have small groups that
start to coalesce and work on changing
those things that affect and condition
human experience in human behavior at
scale like media right like I like
education like economics that that's a
key part of the understanding it takes
everybody but not at first so we've got
some really juicy brilliant questions
from the audience and about 25 minutes
the rapid-fire through them so here's
what we're gonna do for this final round
I want all I want you to really tune in
if this is your question and if it's
your question jump on it and and answer
it as concisely as you can and we'll
move on to the next once we get through
through some really good content here so
this first one's a bit of a challenge
this first one is a challenge to guide
us through a visualization on how the
perfect storm unfolds to guide us
through this transition in the best case
scenario to reach an intelligent
collaborative sustainable system model
and particularly help us visualize the
best case scenario steps that unfold to
get us there no pressure you want this
to be fast
go for it Jordan it's made that we need
in an order of magnitude between five
and ten as significant as the trim
pocalypse to have enough of an impact on
people's consciousness to cause enough
people to detach from their existing
dependence on legacy systems and be
willing to take the risk to jump into
novelty space but if it's more than 10
or 20 times as large as the Trump
pocalypse
that begins to create negative cascade
effects so look at something like
ideally we would have some kind of very
significant economic collapse that would
be best-case scenario like if we could
imagine having hyperinflation where all
dollars are worth nothing tomorrow
that'd be a godsend that would actually
move almost everybody in - oh this thing
that sucks anyway it doesn't work
anymore let me be an experimenting on
the ground without things blowing up
right blowing up is bad imaginary stuff
going away is good so that's a good good
rule of thumb to degree to which you can
get on the order of about 250,000 people
beginning to interconnect with each
other and also connect with at least 12
people on an individualized basis so
that's about three million people in a
meshwork building the kinds of practices
that we've been talking about that's
probably critical mass in the United
States globally it's a different story
there's all kinds of different rate
dynamics I don't know exactly how it
plays out there that's a decent
framework though so if you can imagine
scaling this - how many people are here
about 300 so scaling this by two orders
of magnitude three doors of magnitude
that's probably the right kind of
framework to be able to maneuver us
across a transition the other big piece
that would be fantastic as I mentioned
is if we could get a critical mass of
elites in the next two or three years
that's where things get very sketchy we
don't have a lot of time for that we
need to get a critical mass of elites to
be able to actually be willing to take
the risk that the game they won is going
away and they're gonna be the folks who
are gonna make the next game happen we
might be able to do without that but
probably not I have a quick one so in
the intermediate transition phase
imagine a world that basically doesn't
have any intellectual property taxes and
then for the long game
imagine a world where everybody
understood the full meaning of this
simple idea love is that which enables
choice you really get that if you really
really get that if you live by that
principle if everybody in the world
understood that thoroughly the world
wouldn't would absolutely be a better
place as cliche as it is teeing up the
next question you talk about forming a
collective that's aligned in feeling
deeply interconnected what is the
toolbox to keep us accountable to that
state specific actions we could all be
doing to keep ourselves accountable to
really living in that state of
interconnectivity
whatever you want to call it so we have
this idea that you we want to maintain a
particular condition and there was a
question that was asked about you know
who's gonna be the enforcers of the loss
who's gonna make the loss and this
question strikes me as being very
similar in some respects how do we
maintain an integrity state we can't do
it by having a special class of people
that is essentially the enforcers the
police you know that's just another
version of the Stanford Prison
Experiment and although it moves very
slowly it ends up very ugly and you
can't do it by basically trying to have
everybody become the policeman and
watching everyone else that basically
erodes what there's a sense of
individual sovereignty and privacy it
makes you essentially subject to the
tyranny of the consensus and in effect
you end up not being able to do anything
at all because there's always going to
be somebody out there is going to
disagree with the basic premise of what
you're talking about so in effect we
need a third model we need something
that is neither you know the sort of
top-down kind of structured
organizational model of trying to create
consensus or we're essentially the sort
of bottom-up thing which is just you're
gonna take so long that no one's ever
gonna actually come to agreement before
the problem in crisis has already passed
right we need something that's faster
than that and yet not necessarily has
the disadvantages of the top-down
technique the kind of model that comes
to mind for me is is sort of this
peer-to-peer relationship that computers
can set up to be add you have a protocol
of communication and if neither computer
is is you know disagreeing about the
protocol then an effective transaction
happens information moves across one
machine to another
well nobody is essentially the enforcer
of the protocol if you don't speak the
protocol if you don't know how to speak
the language you don't end up
communicating all right the transactions
that are necessary to to move resources
around just don't happen because nobody
wants to talk to you so in effect the
real thing here is is that you can't
enforce communication but by having
communication by you know learning the
language and learning to develop some
sort of consensus technology of having
the conversation that that process tends
to enforce itself Nate mother nature
doesn't need some enforcer to enforce
natural laws to in a sense create
coherency it just happens it's just part
of the system it's something that's
built in and in the same sort of way we
want to look at having the integrity of
the system having the integrity of the
civilization having the anti fragile
characteristic be something that's
intrinsic to the process itself that if
a crime was performed that the action of
the crime is its own worst punishment
for the person performing it that's what
we're looking for
wonderful so this I'm really glad this
next question was asked as it was
something that we all faced in winning
this event on is gaining a holistic
perspective we've talked about the
importance of diversity we've talked
about the importance of women leadership
in this new phase that we're going
through and yet here we sit right is for
white men and so how do we gain that
holistic perspective how do we continue
to really encourage diversity and ensure
diversity as we're building this new
civilization this new system it's not
just that it's diversity it's that it's
integration right if we just have
everything the same you don't have
enough integration there's not enough
variation in the system and if you have
just an emphasis on diversity then you
end up with so many different points of
view but no integration that doesn't
work either you want to have something
which is essentially an integration of
enough diversity that essentially you
have really encountered reality if
you're trying to solve a problem and you
only understand part of what the problem
is because you've only exposed yourself
to that you haven't learned the language
of the solution you haven't become a fit
vehicle to receive
and perceive what a solution would look
like so when effect part of it is is
that by embracing diversity by embracing
other points of view we encounter the
language of the problem space and we
become the kinds of people we become the
kinds of individuals that when we have
the insight we can grasp that feeling
and turn it into a form we can write
down the answer because we know the
language of the problems base we have
made ourselves an expert in the kind of
spaces that a solution exists in without
going through the work of actually
having the encounter with the problem
without having exposed yourself fully to
the nature of what the real situation is
you know we talked about Brett earlier a
person that has deep evolutionary
biological experience he's a person that
I view as crucial to informing me about
the kinds of issues that occur at a
biological level because without
accounting for those kinds of things our
solutions are incomplete we in a sense
need to understand the full
ramifications of the problem which means
that we we need to have Omni
consideration means we've got to
basically see from enough perspective so
that we can combine and synthesize
something that our intuition can
actually speak to and that our intellect
can grasp Daniel in tune in Daniel
Jordan tune in so in biology we have
this topic of an adaptive landscape so
in in a landscape you've got multiple
peaks and multiple valleys so as
nature's evolving and we see increased
orderly complexity and kind of a
movement of new emergent more complex
creatures right like with humans kind of
at the end of that chain so far viruses
are still evolving - right corals are
still evolving - there's a whole bunch
of different things that are adaptive
and then there's some things that are
not adaptive the same is going to be
true in the future of civilization it's
not going to be a homogeneous here is
the worldview or here is the aesthetic
that everyone has there will be an
adaptive landscape of a number of ways
of being a number of aesthetics a number
of ways of thinking about things in
problem-solving that are all adaptive
that are all functional that all meet
the necessary and sufficient criteria
for a civilization that's viable and
that means that there can be meaningful
relationship across
right not just inexorable an
unrecoverable dysfunction between them
so it's like do we want diversity well
some the kinds of diversity that lead to
inexorable breakdown in conflict
we don't want right but there's a truth
part in those elements that we need to
be able to hold the kinds of diversity
that lead to multiple perspectives that
lead to synergy and emergence is
critical so synergy across a bunch of
the same thing doesn't really happen
right synergy across homogeny you don't
get very much emergent property so this
is it you know this is a key dynamic one
thing I would say about it is so how do
we seek out different perspectives we
have a friend who just did his PhD
dissertation on studying higher stages
of human development within which as
soon as you even say that
it bothers people right what does it
mean higher stage and yet development
isn't nothing right and one of the key
things that he identified was something
that had been previously thought to be a
key definer which was perspective taking
the ability to take multiple
perspectives was less relevant than
perspective seeking the ability the the
predisposition to seek lots of
perspectives and then the capacity to
actually do it well and then the ability
to synthesize across those but the most
critical part that they identified was
the impetus to actually seek other
perspectives so this is important one
thing else I'll say about it is it's
hard notice how many times has happened
for you where someone has a worldview
that actually bugs the out of you
right that where there's something that
you feel is sacred that it seems like
their their worldview doesn't care about
and could even damage and you're just
willing to inside go to war with them
but again we just define that moving
forward all wars are lose-lose so what
does it mean to be like ok how do I deal
with this
so one thing I would say is to just
actually sit in that we have to and
figure it out it's a part of it actually
piggyback Jordans been burning here and
we want to move on so you have the quick
30 second move on you got something
divorced there are no necessary value
conflicts Daniel was just asking a
question if you have somebody that seems
that they value publicly if you go know
something there's no aspect of those
values which necessarily are mutually
exclusive have that as an idea and try
it out see where you go
Daniel you mentioned emergence and
you're often sharing that principle and
so the question is can we rely on
emergence can we do the work
individually to be available for
emergence to happen and if we do that
will that allow things to transition
smooth and fast enough or is there
something we need to be doing in
addition to that to bring about this new
civilization
perfect
right I'm seriously I need to actually
think about that I think that we can't
we can't rely on the notion of emergence
I think that if we try to rely on the
notion of emergence that we are in
effect you know having a kind of false
hope we have to work to create that kind
of emergency because there's there's an
effort that's involved between here and
there I think that emergence will
actually happen but I think there will
only happen if we don't take it for
granted the end result which is it's not
it's actually the question is not well
formed that's not the way to think about
it the way to think about it is to tune
into who you are and what you're here to
do and do that completely and if
everybody did that do you think that
would be enough to guide us through this
transition it doesn't matter yeah I
think I have to agree with Jordan on
this is it is it going to be enough to
get to the transition is an unanswerable
question for anyone right now
we're trying really hard to just
identify the concepts that we think
might be the attributes of what solution
might look like what characteristics
does a solution need to have that list
at this particular point is unbounded we
don't know whether everything on it is
necessary we don't know whether it's
sufficient we know it's important to ask
the question of what sort of
characteristics our solution what sort
of things do we need to develop you know
I think you're right Jordan that the
questions of some extent is not well
formed but it's interesting I will spend
some more time thinking about
which knowing forests means you will
write a definitive essay in the next 48
hours did an email sent to three people
will ignore it though getting into
really practical daily ritual what would
you recommend as a daily ritual practice
for healing and the self work necessary
to be fully available at this moment
meditation is important if you don't
spend a little bit of time by yourself
getting to know who you are
if you don't spend some time basically
learning what is the vehicle that is
your life you know you got to spend at
least a little bit of time to yourself
every day usually first thing in the
morning if you if you become truly self
aware if you know the influence that
people have on you because you know who
you are in the absence of all influence
then you can begin to account for the
effect that you have on other people
which is layering the other side of that
which is friends friends are hard like
friends if you if you have not yet
figured out how to actually have friends
that's the next thing and if you have by
the way there are a lot of people who
haven't figured that out and we most
people just play next to each other
anybody knows people know how to play
with each other seriously like holding
people to the standard of doing what
what he just said right holding people
to the standard of absolutely not
holding back from who being exactly who
they're supposed to be is what a
friend's supposed to do that is hard so
if you do this and you do that I think
you've got about as good an answer as
you're gonna get
probably
when Jordan said on the last question
work on becoming who you are here to be
an offering doing what is yours to do
and that that's really it that is all of
you right it is not purely intellect
evelopment
or heart development or will
developments or personal or
interpersonal it's all those things and
emergence happens at the intersection of
all those happening right so if is it
relevant to work through childhood
traumas that make us shut down or not
willing to face certain things or create
certain kinds of emotional
predispositions that lead to cognitive
predisposition yes it is necessary is it
sufficient no is it necessary to develop
our critical thinking so we can actually
see is this fact a fact or not yes is it
sufficient no so if you think about what
whatever system if you talk about left
and right brain or mind heart and whale
or all the chakras all the systems of
intelligence and capacity that any
system that looked at what the human
organism is they all need progressively
more developed and then not just the
person but the person with other people
in the environment when you can operate
as a truly whole integrated human being
then you can be available to meet in
community so perhaps this next question
will take us a little deeper on this
topic
what are the rate limiters that are
unnecessarily slowing down our ability
to live from a state of feeling
interconnected to all life and how do we
remove these rate limiters so that we
quicken humanity's evolution
I think there's an awful lot of
fragmentation in our communication
process you know our message medium to
one another in the form of social media
and Twitter and stuff like that Facebook
and all the rest they they encourage us
to say shorter things and we don't get a
chance to sort of sink into what
somebody really means it's like we're
overwhelmed with this avalanche of
incoming sensory data and most of it is
noise we want to in effect try to come
into a space where we get to have depth
as much as we have frequency personally
I would rather speak to a few people
really really well than have just
acquaintances with a thousand that's a
rate limiter on civilization
one of the primary limiters the way that
we went about fabricating an identity
that worked particularly in middle
school and high school to be able to
allow us to endure and survive the
perhaps of the crisis that is reality
that we live in right now and of course
what that does is that means you don't
engage in a lot of stuff that we're
talking about and that thing and I guess
my called ego mind here tries to protect
itself and inhibits thinking and it
reacts to things and so nothing works if
you've got that in between you and other
people so that's another major rhythm
there the nice thing about that is that
you're actually needed you can just get
rid of it it's a turn-off and then go
back to being an authentic being so
we've got one last question that's for
all three of you and that is what is
your big bet I know you've formed a
think tank called deep code there's a
limited amount of time there's a limited
amount of resource what's your big bet
and where the biggest leverages do you
want to do functional groups Oh God
I think that for my own part I'm
basically having the hypothesis that
there is a theory of ethics that will
allow us to close the ethical gap that
will allow us to move from a
consideration of choice effective choice
good choices which is heretofore open
based purely on the notion of opinion to
something which has a rigorous more
mathematical character which isn't to
say that I'm expecting that choices be
made only on the basis of some
intellectual premise but that by
combining the hearts and the value
systems that we have with a toolkit that
allows us to integrate those things in a
sane way then we can move the dialogue
to a position that is considerably
deeper than could be reached by just
simply any single point of view so in
effect I guess you could say that for me
the big bet is whether or not that
ethical system is truly complete and
actually works
I have subjected it to every single test
I can think of I have tried it in my own
business I have tried it in many years
since I have come where and become aware
of these concepts and my hope is is that
that is a component a kind of piece of
architecture that that will actually
work that will hold the weight that is
that is in a sense to be placed on it
so I could say something like my big bet
is transforming macroeconomics and the
because economics can be seen as an
interface layer between our worldview
and infrastructure right our worldview
involves things like what do we value
and who are we and what who is other and
who are what are we connected to and
then that's actually codified in an
economic equation where the whale is
worth something dead and not something
alive and where oxygens not worth that
much because there's lots of it and
scare stuff is worth a lot even if we
don't do anything with it right that the
value equation that then predisposes
what we confer resource to if you do
these things will confer more resource
or we confer power that way which then
ends up determining which technologies
get built which is where the physical
power and the Darwinian senses and how
the how the actual planet and each other
are affected we could say that interface
layer right the transition to
internalizing all the externalities and
we could talk about a few processes to
do that we could talk about a real-time
balance sheet of the Commons where we
have sensor grid an Internet of Things
sensor grid and satellites and people
sensor processes that are informing the
built world and the natural world
Commons where they're actually at in
real time how they're changing and so
rather than have separate balance sheets
that are competing at the expense of
each other in increasingly non-viable
win-lose game theory we can actually
work to increase the comprehensive
integrity of the balance sheet of the
Commons and everyone's generative access
to it the you know we can we never had
when Bucky fuller kind of talked about
that as a possibility the ability to
actually have Commons management we
didn't even have the internet we didn't
have the Internet of Things right we
didn't have those kinds of data science
capabilities but the technologies that
are both forcing us to change because
they're no longer viable also make
possible change right the technological
unemployment that is both going to end
capitalism as we've known it also makes
it possible to in capitalism as we've
known it and make
better systems right so this emergence
is both a half-two and can at the same
time because of capacities so I could
say you know change of economics but can
we change that without changing
infrastructure where we actually have to
build those kinds of technological
systems that don't fully exist yet we
have to build closed-loop you know
material economies production material
economies different waste management
production etc well they inter affect
each other can we change that without
changing worldview and changing media
and education there are there are
theorists that say really worldview is
the main thing and if we can have a more
Omni consider a worldview if we can have
less dysfunctional ego structures etc
that'll change everything there
theorists who like cultural materialism
say actually the tools into predisposing
behaviors and if you change the tools
that's the only thing that's really ever
changed anything there are other
theorists say well actually that series
of social system incentives and drivers
end up changing to me I see them as
inter effecting and co-arising and so
there is not a solution in there that is
even realizable independent of a handful
of other things that have to Co arise so
the the you know what I'd be putting my
bet on is a minimum necessary and
sufficient set of transforms that make
possible a fundamentally new and viable
civilization structure to answer that
question I had to kind of think back on
what is my big bet like whenever I made
a big bet and in it's interesting to
notice for me that I'm an intrinsically
a person who operates through portfolio
theory so I don't tend to make big bets
I tend to make distributed risk and a
long time ago I came to the conclusion
that the only viable approach was
something called collective intelligence
which is to say we don't yet know how to
do any of the things that we need to do
and the only way to do it is we actually
have to learn first how to be much much
better at knowing how to do
things and I worked really hard on that
for a long time and about four years ago
I hit the wall and I recognized that I
could not get where I wanted to get
unless I was willing to place my big bet
my big bet was love which for many
people here that may not seem like that
big thing but you should understand that
up until about four years ago I'd acted
she really didn't have any friends so
that's where quite serious when I say
that friendship is hard and being
willing to go into the the crucible of
love which i think is a better way of
describing it and exploring all of its
dimensionality and the the pain and the
healing and that only can come through
that is that I think is the big bet
[Applause]
[Music]
you